so I was thinking about uh The Meta
Sut and just going through that there's
quite a lot in it actually but so we can
stop wherever feels
right so read it verse by
verse so it begins with what should be
done by one skillful in
good so as to gain the state of
Peace it's kind of a question
really well what we spoke
before only the person with the Right
View knows good as good and bad is
bad knows Kusa isusa and Aus is
ausa with which
means that also it applies to somebody
with the Right
View what should be done once you
know is and a is a one who skillful and
good yeah one who knows good is good bad
is bad what should he do to have his
mind in a peaceful state
right says let him be able upright and
straightforward se he already like that
one with thing well there's always room
for improvement so the is upright and
improvement so the is upright and
straight forward from put's point of
view but not from an aran's point of
view yeah say he's easy to speak
yeah say he's easy to speak
to Gentle and not
proud and this gentle who got me it's
not he's not sensitive
you know no that's not what gentle is
like you're non gentle when you have
intentions of
harm if you're
unable to have in to act out of
intentions of harm you're gentle that
doesn't mean you will necessarily come
across is is kind and
gentle because people don't have
criteria for what truly kind and gentle
is or proud exactly yeah not proud he
cannot be rooted in your anything you
con seeit he's
seeit he's
contented mhm easily easy to support
easily satisfied yeah with few tasks and
living very lightly M his faculties are
Serene sure are Serene prudent and
modest un this is unswayed by the
emotions of the
Clans so
unswayed by the emotions of others of
others yeah of other authorities of
other traditions of other
establishments you know when you say the
the rules of a clan means if you belong
to you must obey by that so it's like
belonging to a
greater um identity which is usually
everybody does belongs to some greater
identity to some extent be it culture
religion education or something makes
you belong to the to that group
identity but that actually requires a
wrong view it's rooted in the wrong view that
view it's rooted in the wrong view that
kind of belonging it's rooted in you not
being transparent in regard to your own
individuality so the one who has the
right view who has developed his mind he
cannot then um
ignore the fact that he always remains
enclosed within
himself so then if he ches to follow
what Clan says you should do he'll only
do so cuz he knows good is good and bad
is bad not because the clan said so
right but if you don't know for yourself
you will be going by the words of others
by the authority of others by the
majority majority of others exactly
that's another way of oh well look I
don't understand this I don't understand
that but this is more numerous there's
more people saying this than that so
I'll just go with a majority on this one
means either way you don't understand
your so even say if that majority were
right you are in the wrong CU you're not
understanding for yourself you going
just by the majority of it yeah you're
being swayed
by you got no grounding yourself no
grounding so it's just circumstantial
circumstan circumstantially occurred
that in this instance majority was right
and but you as a rule of thumb go with
the majority out of your own weakness
and basically lack of understanding
that's why literally like for soana when
he develops the Right View
when he
knows say uh even if the whole
world would say the Buddha was wrong or
that's wrong if he knows that is right
he would go with what he knows is right
now from PJ's point of view that sounds
like an extremely arrogant and proud
position who do you think you are you
know better than the entire
world but it's factually he knows better
than the entire world that's what s is
but just think he knows better than
entire world in every single case or
something his thoughts are not rooted in
I am better than the entire world I am
worse or I'm equal his thoughts are
rooted in recognizing is
AA is a is a so wholesome is wholesome
UNH wholesome is UN wholesome so if the
whole world says this is UNH wholesome
but he knows that to be wholesome he
will not go with the entire
world if the whole world says yes this
is is wholesome and he knows that is
wholesome he'll go with it because it's
wholesome not because the entire world
said so so that's how he will not be
swayed by what clients say to do because
he has the internal criteria M which is
and you will never develop that internal
criteria if you never basically uh look
Beyond and make effort to understand
things for yourself on that individual
basis but instead always seek shelter in
the safety of numbers crowd tradition
Authority which is the whole kuta do not
go by the majority for its own sake by
the tradition find out for
yourself and many people kind of think
they understand that oh yes of course
find out for myself experience for
myself personal truth yet when it comes
to that to drilling their views down
it's going to be well most people say
this that's why I'm right because I just
subscribe to whatever else people say
yeah but do understand that as right
because it's right or do you just
basically seek the safety mhm in the
group and if you do you'll never develop
the right
view or have a peaceful mind well you
will not have a peaceful mind without a
Right View yes there is no peace without
understanding there is no understanding
without a Right
View there is safety in the numbers by
the way it's not that the safety you get
from the group or majority or belonging
to a tradition or a group identity it's
not that it's not safe it's not that
it's not real it is but it's
flawed so it's not a true
safety it's not the safety that you
seek so it's only something that's sort
of closest to safety that you know but
if you look at it properly investigate
it you realize actually it's not a
safety it's safety of ignorance doesn't
matter what the size of the group is the
fact is I don't know for myself that
what they say it's right thus it's on
the level of my choosing to believe that
they are right because it makes me feel
comfortable even if I happen to be why
it's all secondary it's all secondary
yeah exactly yeah yeah yeah I mean you
can find the right group the group of
arant yeah but if you seek the shelter
of the if you seek the safety basically
and and and follow what they say just so
you'll be safe not because you you
understood it you won't be safe so you
can live with a Buddha himself and
you'll still be
Aug cuz you're not allowing it basically
to penetrate on the levels it should
which isn't that individual basis of
recognition of fundamental not safety
non safety fundamental exposure of
existence fundamental impermanence fear
and all of
that and that's always why people go
with that that even if you know often
you saw that like you know living in the
various monasteries and stuff people
would would sometimes follow or come
having been following certain teachings
that they know themselves were not
adequate because they've been doing for
20 years and still having overcome
things that
even they made them start practicing but
they couldn't give it up because there's
nothing else left which means they would
have to then accept their individual
responsibility for that exposure and not
knowing so although they know the
teachings they've been following were
not adequate they're still too afraid to
admit that to themselves so that's like
oh it didn't work for me but have you
understood it or no have you you made
the effort to understand so what did you
to what extent you you must have some
understanding if you recognize that it
doesn't work for you what is that
understanding why it doesn't work for
you is it because it's inadequate so
already have a sense of oh this is
inadequate but you feel afraid to take
responsibility for that own
recognition and instead I'll just
pretend and ignore the inadequacy so I
can still partake in the safety of
numbers safety of tradition safety of
established norm and so
on safety of the meditation
method yeah the comfort zone I know what
I'm doing I know how to do this I I kind
of at the back of my mind know that it
hasn't resulted in things I was hoping
it doesn't result in things that the
suta say it should result but yes it's
it's less
uncomfortable than if I go against
it and and and do away with
it feel less
exposed if you pretend there is no
problem so unswayed by the emotions of
the plans and let him never do the slightest
plans and let him never do the slightest
thing that other wise men might hold
blameable so the wise man so the other
man with Right View would hold blameable
so what is blameable a wrong view is the
most blame wordy thing so let him not
entertain wrong view in any extent in
regard to anything even for a second cuz
that's the most blame worded thing but
other killing stealing cheating lying
all wise men agree that is UNH wholesome
and you know for yourself it's un
wholesome now you might not necessarily
at that stage you might not necessarily
see sensuality as directly un
wholesome but by the extension of the
principles you have understood by the
extension of that wisdom you can safely
assume that it's most likely un
wholesome and then act
accordingly and restrain yourself and
then you will come to realize that it
wasn't
wholesome but also he's he's he's not
swayed by the emotions of the clan but
Heist listens to oh yeah exactly because
he's not conceited yeah he does not
dismiss the Clans because he is
self-centered and proud he's not swayed
by their emotions doesn't mean he he has
no perspective on their
emotion which equally then means he will
also have perspective on that which is
factual wisdom so even if somebody does
not belong to the clan he approves of or
he was born with or or brought up with
would recognize when somebody says
something that is correct that is along
the principle of is is so he would
recognize wisdom in
others but I mean from from a point of
view of a PJ without a Right View that
sounds like the most conceited
thing all the teachers say this all the
Buddhist Traditions say this who do you
think you are saying the opposite now
sure it is possible that one who is
saying the opposite might be doing
simply because he's so conceited so he
just wants to go against everybody
else but then you listen what else that
person has to say is it just a mad rent
or are they making sense in other
regards as well and then you realize oh
well they are which means even if the
whole world says one
thing there is something to this so
maybe it's worth investigating it
certainly not worth dismissing it just because
not worth dismissing it just because
majority does not agree with it I mean
fundamentally there is only one Buddha
in the world when it arises there are no
two Buddhas it's impossible to be at the
same time which means the Buddha is as
alone as he
gets he's the only the
first sole being that's against the
grain of the entire universe not just
the this
world and yeah when that man met him
straight after his Enlightenment when
say you look so calm who who whose
teaching did you follow cuz this man
assumed you must follow someone some
tradition some observant some tradition
and the Buddha factually said I follow
no one's teaching I'm My Own guide I'm
the supreme leader of
men pure
facts but how did this man take it all
right so be it good for you
and walked
off he did not believe him and he
thought look at this conceited
fool so that's I mean that should not be
a criteria yeah he might be he might
have been factually say a person who
declares that might be factually
conceited or just just sort of being
argumented or just going against
whatever like steering things
up but then you listen what else they
have to say and then you'll see oh wait
there is something more to this it's not
that they're just negating they're
providing reasons for the negating
they're providing rational explanations
they're tie in with other things that
you know could be interpreted that
way and if that's the case then you
should investigate it further and then
use that as a criteria not because oh
100 people say one thing and one person
says the other thus he's wrong
and sometimes people even know that
person in in um in minority is not wrong
but I still try to argue point that you
should still go with the majority and
not disturb the established order of
majority that is true only when the if
when non-disturbing of the established
order of the clans of the tradition
would not go against the message you
have so if you can go with the order
without compromising the message that
you have which is against what the
order's message is then it's fine you
can go with the order but if you can if
going with the order means compromising
the message that you have that is
correct that the whole order disagrees
with then you shouldn't go over the
order you should stick with the message
cuz well that's the only thing that
matters Right View or wrong view the
wrong view as the budha say is the most
blame worthy thing more blame worthy
than killing stealing cheating and
everything else it's the utmost single
blame wory thing in entire Universe in
entire samsar mhm thinking to know that
which you
don't holding on to a view without
questioning it without understanding
it it goes It goes to becomes a bit
different this
this start to talk about uh what this
person should be
thinking in terms of that matter
peaceful mind he said let him think in
safety and in happiness May creatures
all be of a happy
mind whatever breathing beings they may
be no matter what they
are uh May creatures all be of happy
mind let no one work for another's
undoing or even slight him at all
anywhere
and never let them wish each other ill
and so
on so there's this this is what he
should be thinking yeah so on the level
of your thoughts do not
entertain even slightest
like negative
animosity ill will and so on even like
doesn't matter doesn't matter what
happens to you doesn't matter on account
of
what things happen to you doesn't matter
from whom from what type of
being don't have limited mind towards
them but if you because most people take
this and say okay this is the Mantra
that I must now say a million times I
say it a million times in safety and
Bliss M just not and on and on and on
and on and on and
on and you do that do that do that do
that well you ask yourself does
repeating a mantra
cultivate maintain the understanding of
the point of that Mantra or is it
actually quite the opposite focusing on
repeating the Mantra means ignoring the
fact that it needs to be
understood because if you so if you had
to I remember doing a similar
thing a
longer repeating c not certain phrases may my
repeating c not certain phrases may my
mother be well may my sister this may I
be this that that and you generate it's
quite a pleasant thought and you have
pleasant feelings and you feel good you
just feel yeah but that's not what it
says there it says you should cultivate
that mind the state of mind that has no
animosity towards anything breathing of
any kind and you don't cultivate State
of Mind by repeating the random
words cuz if that would be the case the
would would have said so just Chan this
and you'll be purified yet whenever he
talked about it he talked about it in a
dismissive manner of the other brahmanic
Traditions they would doing and he would
criticize them for chanting vas without
understanding what they're chanting so
they're just parting basically the
verses cuz they developed the belief
that the verses in themselves carry
magic of purification and then he said
that even the original brahin that sort
of compile those Raiders and and and the
wisdom in them they actually understood
them that's why they were B in men
mhm brahans of the old day they
understood the verses they understood
the meaning they were not just chanting
them so if you chant for the sake of
remembering it for the sake of then
reflecting on it to understand it of
course but if you chant because you
believe that chanting purifies as you
and maintains your mind of non-ill will
it's utterly completely wrong view so
like these people say this I I will say
that as well and we yeah and that's how
I will partake in that yeah I'm safe I'm
in it so I will just go by the hear say
tradition and repeating words of others
by mere repeating words of others I will
purify myself that's basically
practically what that view is for those
who believe they just chanting with
purify but let him think let him think
about this let him reflect upon it let
him reflect let him develop the state of
mind that is
that is
Limitless that that includes all these
things you can have animosity
towards so you develop a state of mind
free from
animosity that's all the things within
that that you could hate you cannot hate
because hate is rooted in the state of
mind not in things that you
hate so you can also ask yeah you think
about it in safety and in happiness May
creatures all be of think about those
about guidelines for your contemplation
why why do okay so the said nothing that
why is
that or if you can't figure out why take
the Buddha's word and Trust then figure
out how to achieve that so how will I
have a one state of mind they will not
hate this wide array of diverse beings and
this wide array of diverse beings and
objects is that achievable by chasing
down the DI it of the objects or is it
achievable by maintaining the uniformity
of one non-hateful mind which is more
likely is it about cultivating the
pleasure of a particular
of a particular
thought and the avoidance of the
displeasure of not another particular
thought another thought yeah or is it
cultivating a thought that is above
either yeah pleasure or displeasure yeah
the answers of his yeah
exactly it continues and just
as a mother with her life
protects her only
child so let him then for every living
thing protect his boundless mind so we
spoke about it before translation it's
quite obvious you have contemporary
obvious you have contemporary
translation that skew that and they
basically imply that as the mother
protects a child you protect all these
living beings doesn't say so let him
protect every living being like his own
child it says let him protect his one
mind like the mother protects one child
one son
literally cuz by so your only
son that's your only that's your mind
your mind is your only child so you will
not forget about cultivation protection
and mainten of that child cuz if you do
it could die and it could result in your
own death so if you protect your mind as
your only child you will automatically
protect all living beings because when
there is action of non protection of all
living beings it's not rooted in those
beings or non those being it's rooted in
your mind of ill will so if you protect
your mind from ill will it's impossible
no Act of ill will can be exercised
towards anything in the world so by
proxy then you protect the entire world
and that's how the bu explain arand by
practicing for his own benefit practices
for the benefit of the whole
universe yeah but we want to yeah people
want to see well no most people that
internal transparent Dimension is is not
transparent it's they don't see it so
they measure goodness or or non-
goodness by the level of Engagement with
others and with the world so from that
point of view of a of of an ignorant
penous view arant is the most selfish
person in the world swayed by the
emotions yeah s by the emotions of
others exactly using using the measure
of emotions for whether things are good
or bad this makes us feel good thus it's
good and you see ironically then many
people approach DH practice rooted in
that M oh I'll practice freedom from my
dependence on Feelings by following what
makes me feel good it's a contradiction
in
terms that's what we said that in the
previous one of the previous talks I
don't remember what order we shared him
but um if you just you don't need to
practice kindness and uh non-ill will
towards the world or towards anyone in
particular just practice it towards
whatever present feeling is in doing in
your experience and you've covered and
you covered the entire
world anything to
breathe you cannot hate because you stop
resisting the discomfortable feeling
that's presently enduring and if you
truly want to help that's the only way
you can help yeah can have a desire to
help but you can choose to
ignore understanding what is truly
helpful on account of that desire or you
can choose to not ignore and make the
effort to understand what is truly
helpful so what is truly helpful is the
mind of non-ill
Will and if you can do that then you can
potentially teach others to do that of
course yeah which protects them yeah because
yeah which protects them yeah because
you can build people houses food give
them food that's all mundane mundane
pertaining to the world never it's not
you can do that if if that your goal but
you can't expect to do that and practice
Dum at the same time CU those goals are
mutually exclusive if you can help others and not
exclusive if you can help others and not
compromise the lifestyle that's
dedicated to practicing the dhama that
you understood that's fine of course
somebody's drowning you pull them out
they like oh well I will teach them D in
this 3 seconds before they
drown but if you dedicate your life to
saving people from drowning in those
particular instances and on account of
that neglect your own mind your own
child of non your will well that's
doesn't help
anyone the the help is very limitting
very fleeting yeah not
substantial above below and all around
untroubled with no
enemy and while he stands walks sits or
lies down free from
drowsiness let him resolve upon this
mindfulness yeah this is the peaceful
life yeah you cannot
resolve upon things that are not
clear like there's instances in the
sutas of of a person who becomes Aran by
resolving upon
wisdom so he resolves upon that which he
gain Insight with wisdom
right so in order to resolve upon
something you need to know what that
is you need to be clear about it you
need to be familiar with it you need to
have made the effort to remove any
opaqueness any ambiguity in regard to
the meaning and nature of it keep once
it's sufficiently clear that's when that
resolve can occur and that's when you
can maintain that resolve and that's why
it can result in our
hardship it say free from drowsiness but
free from free from sloth free from lack
of clarity free from laziness in regard
to maintain the clarity m
m
not somehow energetic like magical
energy or free from uh he's not
tied he's got this abundant energy
flowing through his body yeah of love no
it's not no it refers to the clarity of
the meaning yeah which is why you can
resolve upon it with mindfulness
not this energy of love you can be tired
but tiredness does not induce
[Music] um losing the sight of the right context
um losing the sight of the right context
does not induce forgetting about your
only child yeah you're tired but you're
still clear about what's important yeah
you're still clear about what you must
protect you still protect it and then
when you're notti you protect it even
more you cultivate it
the last verse is he when he when he
[Applause] has when he's not holding to any views M
has when he's not holding to any views M
he's virtuous and has perfected seeing
and purges Greed from for sensual
desires he surely not holding to wrong
views yeah not holding to wrong views
virtuous perfect in knowledge and
see free from Central desires he he no
longer gets born again that's when
become it goes beyond the views that's
what it means right so you need the
right view in order to overcome the
wrong views but for an AR hunt basically
he overcomes even the Right
View that's that Su has the Noble Path
and for an AR it's like a tenfold
path whereby he overcomes even the that
dependence on The View the right view
the right criteria he even distinguishes
that so he he he resolves upon Clarity
with the Right View yeah you maintain it
you cultivate it until it ripens and
then even that falls off yeah it's like
once you use the raft that you built you
cross the shore and then you leave the
raft yeah and when do you leave the raft
well you know when you're safe on the
other side of the shore it's like
halfway through pedaling oh do I have
abandon raft now or you cannot doubt it
cuz it's not up to you anymore say that
you abandon this raft when you get toore
th I'll abandon now right right right
yeah and be on I'll preemptively abandon
it because you shouldn't hold on to
anything yeah yeah no then that's often
misunderstood I know in the same like
the Contemporary chanting of that like
not hold to any views or they even now I
think since in some translation don't
hold to fixed views it's like well
that's a fixed view I shall not hold to
fixed views is your fixed View and there
is no way out of that except finding the
right type of fixed view which is the
fixed view of soan that he developed
through understanding the Buddhist
teaching then using that fixed view to
overcome all the kind of underlying
Tendencies and kesas and so on then that
fixed view will wither away as
well and that's when you out
hand but people think oh if I abstain
from declaring my view I somehow scate
between the views and I will be free
from the views by not holding on to
views which is the view that I
hold so that last verse refers to the
arship so the only one truly who can say
I don't hold to any views anymore is the
one whose Right View has withered way
extinguished itself through the right
effort so he went beyond the views
yeah that's the full development of yeah
it's not a choice it's not s to makes a
choice I will not hold to my right View
and he becomes an arant it's a result of
the right practice that the Buddha
outlines there and then says if you
practice like that you will not anymore
be attached to any view even the Right
View you will be an Aran
then but it's the right view that
brought him there it's the raft that
took him to the other show